今天我们要学习另一种形式的加密——可调加密。
In this segment we are gonna look at
another form of encryption called
我将用磁盘加密作为一种应用来给出使用可调加密的理由，
tweakable encryption. I'm gonna motivate
tweakable encryption using disk encryption
并且我们将了解磁盘加密作为确定性加密的另一种应用。
as an application and we'll see disk
encryption as yet another application for
所以磁盘加密的问题就是我们想在磁盘上将扇区加密。
deterministic encryption. So the disk
encryption problem is that we wanna
每个扇区长为4kb，现在的问题是没有扩展空间。
encrypt sectors on disk. Say each sector
is four kilobytes long and the problem is
换句话说，如果扇区大小是4KB，
that there is no space to expand. In other
words if the sector size is four kilobytes
那么密文的大小也必须是4KB，因为
the cipher text size also has to be
exactly four kilobyte because there is
如果密文比文件更大，我们将没有空间存放多余的信息。
nowhere to write the extra bits if the
cipher text was bigger than the plaintext.
我们的目标就是建立一个无扩展的加密，
And so our goal is basically to build a
non expanding encryption where the cipher
并使其密文的大小和主文件大小一样。
text size is identical exactly equal to
the plaintext size. So what does it mean
那么加密不能扩展到底是什么意思呢？严格来说，
that encryption can't expand? Well,
technically we were saying, basically the
就是信息大小和密文大小相等。
message space is equal to the cipher text
space. So the message space will be four
所以信息的大小回事4KB，密文的大小 也是4KB。
kilobyte messages and the cipher text
space would be also four kilobyte
在这种情况下我们必须使用磁盘加密，
messages. In this case clearly we have to
use deterministic encryption because if
因为如果加密是随机的，我们没有空间来存放其随机性。
encryption was randomized there will be no
place to store the randomness. And similarly
同理我们也没有空间存放其完整的数据，因为我们不能扩展密文或增加任何比特。
we have no room for integrity, because we can't
expand the cipher text and add any
因此我们能尽可能做到的是确定的CPA安全，这就是我们的目标。
integrity bits. So the most we can achieve
is deterministic CPA security and that's
那么现在我们有一个很简单的引理需要证明，
going to be our goal. Now it turns out
there's a really simple lemma to
简单来说是如果我们有一个主文件和密文大小相同的
prove, that basically says if you give me
a deterministically CPA secure cipher
确定性CPA安全的密码，也就是不能扩展，
where the message space is equal to the
cipher text space, so no expansion, then in
那么事实上密码就是PRP。那么我们现在讨论的实质是如果我们
fact the cipher is a PRP. So, really all
we're saying here is if we want no
不想扩展，我们加密时唯一的选择就是使用我们在前面的课程中
expansion at all our only option for
encrypting is what we called construction
称作NO.2结构。即我们必须运用PRPR来加密，
number two in the previous segment. Namely
we have to encrypt using a PRP. So, let's
那么让我看看怎么用PRP来加密。我们来看磁盘，将其分解成扇区。
look at how we might encrypt using a
PRP. Well, we take our disk, and we break
现在，如果我们队每一个扇区用相同的密码下的PRP加密，
it into sectors. And now, if we encrypted
every sector using a PRP under the same
我们就遇到了确定性加密的一个通常的问题。
key, we kind of run into our standard
problem with deterministic encryption.
即，如果扇区一和扇区三的某些文件相同，
Namely, if sector one and sector three
happen to have the same plain text, then
那么加密果断扇区一将和加密过的扇区三相等，
the encrypted sector one would be equal to
the encrypted sector three and the
敌手也将知道相关的主文件是相同的。
attacker would learn that the
corresponding plain texts are the same.
这种情况是一个很真实的问题，举个例子，
Now this actually is a real problem for
example, if your, if some of your sectors
如果某些扇区是空白的，你知道它们全部被置零，那么事实上加密的扇区
are empty you know they are all set to
zero then in fact the encrypted sectors
会是完全相同的，因此敌手也将准确的知道在你的硬盘上
would be identical and as a result the
attacked would know exactly which sectors
哪些扇区是空的，哪些不是。所以这事实上是非常棘手的，
on your disk are empty and which sectors
are not. So this is actually quite
那么我们能不能解决得更好些呢。答案是可以。
problematic and the question is, can we do
any better? And so the answer is yes, and
第一个解决的办法是，我们可以对每一个扇区使用不同的密码。
the first idea that comes to mind is well,
why don't we use a different key for every
那么扇区一用密码一来加密，
sector? So you can see sector number one
gets encrypted with key one, sector number
扇区二运用密码而，以此类推。那么现在即使扇区一的内容
two gets encrypted with key two and so on
and so forth. So now even if the content
和扇区三的内容相同，扇区一和扇区三的密文也是不同的
of sector number one is equal to sector
number three the cipher text of sector one
因为他们是通过不同的密码来加密的。
and sector three will be different because
they are encrypted under different keys.
因此这种方法事实上避免了我们前面谈到的纰漏，
So this actually avoids the leakage that
we talked about before although I do want
不过我想指出，使用这种方法也会产生一些纰漏。
to point out that there is still a little
bit of leakage with this mode. For example
例如，如果使用者改变了扇区一种的一比特内容，那么该扇区
if the user happened to change one bit in
sector one and then that sector gets
也相应地加密成不同的密文。这样就会形成误解，
encrypted into a different cipher text. So
this will be garbled all completely,
因为我们使用的是一种伪随机排列，扇区会映射为全新的随机输出，
because this is a pseudo random
permutation, the sector will be-- even if
即使只是改变了原文件中的一比特。
one bit of the plain text changes, the
sector will be just mapped to a completely
然而，如果使用者将这个变化恢复原状，扇区也恢复原来的样子，
new random output. However, if the user
then undoes the change, and reverts back
那么加密扇区也会恢复原样，
to the original sector, then the encrypted
sector will revert back to its original
敌手也会清楚使用者改变了一些信息然后恢复了。
state, and the attacker can tell that a
change was made and then reverted. So,
那么还是有一些信息泄露了。但是对于这种形式的
there's still a little bit of
information leakage. But that type of
信息泄露，我们除了将其牺牲掉以外没有什么办法可以解决。
information leakage, there's really
nothing we can do without really
因此我们将忽视它，将其视为可接受的。
sacrificing performance. So, we're just
going to ignore that and deem that
下一个问题及时现在我们的磁盘事实上容量很大，
acceptable. So the next question is now
you realize our disks are actually getting
扇区很多。这就意味着我们要生成
pretty big and there are lots of sectors.
So this would mean that we are generating
很多很多的密码。但是显然我们不需要存储所有的这些密钥。
lots and lots of keys here, but of course
we don't have to store all these keys, we
我们可以简单地运用一个伪随机函数来生成这些密钥。
can simply generate these keys using a
pseudo random function. So, the way this
这种方式就是我们有一个主密钥，我们称之为K。
would work is we would have a master key
which we would call K. And then the sector
接下来——我们称之为扇区T将用主密钥加密。
number which I'm gonna denote by T is
gonna be encrypted using the master key.
加密的结果将是特别的扇区密钥，
And the result of that encryption would be
the particular sector key, which I'll
我们称之为KsubT。现在
denote by K sub T. Now the reason this is
secured is again because the PRF is
因为PRF在我们的随机函数中是不可区分的，也就是说如果我们
indistinguishable from our random
function, which means that basically if we
为这些扇区一，二，三，四直到L，申请一个随机函数，
apply a random function to these sector
numbers, one, two, three, four, up to L,
他们会在密钥区映射为完全随机的元素，
they basically get mapped to completely
random elements in the key space and as a
因此我们给每个扇区运用一个新的随机的独立的密钥完成了加密。
result we are encrypting every sector
using a new random independent key. So
这是一个完善的结构，那么再来，我们为每一个扇区都要申请PRF，
this is a fine construction, however
again, for every sector we would have to
那么很自然的，我们能不能做得更好些呢？当然是可以的。
apply this PRF. And so the natural
question is, can we do even better? And it
这种方式概念下的可调块密码是
turns out we can. And this introduces this
concept of a tweakable block cipher where
我们有一个主密钥。并且我们希望这个主密钥
really what we want is basically to have
one master key. And we want this one
能派生出许多许多的PRP。所以我们说的一种方法是
master key to derive many, many,
many PRPs. So we said one way to do that
简单的运用密钥K和PRP加密。但是就像我们看到的，还有
is simply encrypt the key K using the PRP
number. But as we'll see, there's a more
跟有效的方法。现在PRP事实上是我们称作一种调整，
efficient way to do that. Now this PRP
number is actually what's called a tweak,
这里引出了可调的概念，一个可调整的块密钥。
and that introduces this concept of
tweakable, a tweakable block cipher. So in
因此在一个可调的块密码中，加密和解密算法通常
a tweakable block cipher, the encryption
and decryption algorithm basically, as
将密钥作为输入，它们将可调作为输入。首字母T就是可调区域的简称。
usual, take a key as input, they take a
tweak as input. This capital T is what's
并且显然它将数据作为输入，
called the tweak space. And of course they
take the data as input and they output
并在X中输出数据。其性质是在随机密钥的可调区中做每一次调整。
data in the set X. The property is such that for
every tweak in a tweak space in a random
一般来说如果我们设置了密钥和调整，我们将得到一个可逆函数
key. Basically if we fix the key and the
tweak, then we end up with an invertible
一个在X重点一对一的函数。并且因为密钥是随机的，
function, a one to one function on the
set X. And because the key is random with
函数事实上也是不可分辨的。
the, the function is in fact
indistinguishable from random. In other
换句话说，对于每一套调整，我们得到一个PRP，
words, for every setting of the tweak, we
basically get a PRP, an independent PRP
一个从X到X的独立的PRP。正如我所说，我们现在申请的就是
from X to X. And as I said, the
application for this is now we're going to
要将扇区编号用作调整，因此每一个扇区
use the sector number as the tweak, and as
a result, every sector is going to get its
都能得到他自己的独立的PRP。那么我快速地定义一下
own independent PRP. So let me very, very
quickly just define more precisely what is
安全可调分组密码的实质。正如我们所说有一个可调区。有密钥，
a secure tweakable block cipher. So as we
said there's a tweak space. There's a key,
可调区，和不可见的区域X。通常，我们定义两个实验。
a tweak space and an [inaudible] space X.
And as usual, we define our two
在实验一中我们要做的是
experiments. Here in experiment one what's
gonna happen is we are gonna choose a
选择一个随机序列。不只是一个序列，我们要选择
truly random set of permutations. So not
just one permutation we're gonna choose as
和调整数目一样数目的序列。那么可以明白这就是为什么我们
many permutations as there are tweaks. So
you notice this is why we raise this to the
将这个增加至可调区的大小。如果可调区的大小是5，这就是说我们要
size of the tweak space. If the size of
the tweak space is five, this says we are
在X中选择5个随机序列。在另一种情况中，
choosing five random permutations on the
set X. And in the other case, basically,
我们要选择随机密钥，并且我们将用之前在可调区中的调整
we're just gonna, you know, choose a
random key, and we're gonna define our set
来定义这一套序列。
of permutations as the ones defined by
the, by tweaks in the tweak space. And
并且敌手将模仿调整和X区。
then the adversary basically gets to
submit a tweak and an X. And he gets to
并且他将可以得到被用调整T1来定义的序列的值，在X1点所求的值。
see the value of the permutation defined
by the tweak T1, evaluated at the point
并且他将可以得到这些很多次。再继续，
X1. And he gets to see this again and
again. And again, he gets to see the value
就得到了排列T2的值，再评估X2的值，这么一步一步下去。
of the permutation defined by the tweak
T2, evaluated at the point X2, and so on
之后他的目标是要判断与其相互作用的排列是否为真正的随机排列。
and so forth. And then his goal is to say
whether he interacted with truly random
如果他做不到
permutations, or pseudo random
permutations. And if he can't do it, we
我们就能说此可调分组密码是安全的。而与常规分组密码不同的是
say that this tweakable block cipher is
secure. So the difference from a regular
在常规分组密码中，你只能与一个排列作用。
block cipher, is, in a regular block
cipher, you only get to interact with one
而你的目标则是判断这个排列为真或假
permutation. And then your goal is to tell
whether you're interacting with a
这里你则要与随机排列T相互作用
pseudorandom permutation or a truly random
permutation. Here you get to interact with
然后你的目标又是判断随机排列T是否为真正的随机排列
T random permutations. And again your goal
is to tell whether the T random
照例如果你不能
permutations are truly random or
pseudorandom. So as usual if you can't
分清，如果敌手在两个实验中的表现相同，我们就说
distinguish, if the adversary behaves the
same in both experiments, we say that this
这个PRP是一个安全调控的REP。来看一些例子
PRP is a secure tweakable PRP. Okay. Very
good. So let's look at some examples. So
我们已经见过的一个小例子
we already looked at, at the trivial
example. In the trivial example, what we do,
假设密钥空间和输入空间大小一致
we just, we're gonna assume that the key
space is equal to the input space. So this
这个RPR的作用为，将X*X的值赋给X
PRP really acts on, you know, X times X to
X. So think of AES for example, where
我们考虑AES,假设考虑键空间的大小为128比特，数据空间为128比特，输出也为128比特
the key space is 128 bits, the data space
is 128 bits and of course the output is
再次找到一个分组可调密码
128 bits and then the way that we defined a
tweakable block cipher again there is a
有一个密钥，一个变形和数据的输入是基于使用我们的主键来加密的
key, a tweak and data as input is
basically we encrypt the tweak using our
随后我们用得到的随机密钥来加密数据
master key and then we encrypt the data
using the resulting random key. Now
如果我们要通过可调分组密码来加密n个分组
you realize that if we wanted to encrypt n
blocks with this tweakable block cipher,
这就需要2n个估值分组密码，n个估值用于加密给定的变形
this would require 2n evaluations of
the block cipher: n evaluations to encrypt
其他的n个估值则用于加密实际所给的数据
the given tweaks, and then n more evaluations
to encrypt the actual given data.
这里有一个很好的例子，可以告诉我们实际上可以做的更好
So, I want to show you a nice example,
that shows that we can actually do better.
这就叫做XTS结构。它实际上基于
This is called the XTS construction.
It's actually originally based on
一个被Phil Rogaway命名为XEX的模型。它按后续所说运行
a mode called XEX due to Phil Rogaway.
And it works as follows. So suppose you
假设有一个常规分组加密用于加密n比特的分组
give me a, a regular block cipher that
operates on n-bit blocks. So not a
并不是可调分组加密，仅仅只是一个常规分组加密
tweakable block cipher, just a regular
block cipher. We're gonna define a
我们想要定义一个可调分组加密，而它将会用两个密钥作为输入
tweakable block cipher. So again, this
tweakable block cipher is gonna take two
为了方便，你要马上看到的调整空间
keys as input. The tweak space, for
convenience, which you're gonna see in
我们将假设这个调整空间由两个值T和I组成
just a minute, we're gonna assume this
tweak space is made up of, of two values,
T将作为我们马上能看到的调整值
T and I. T is going to be some, you know, some
tweak value which we'll see in a minute, and I is
而I则将作为索引。X将为n比特字符串
going to be some index. And then X is
going to be an n-bit string which we're
我们将运用可调分组加密在X上。接下来就是XTS的运行方式
going to apply the tweakable block cipher
to. So, the way XTS works is as follows.
首先我们要加密左边一般的变形
The first thing we're going to do is we're
going to encrypt the left half of the
也就是T，运用密钥K2,，得到的结果为N
tweak, namely T, using the key K2 and we're
going to call the result N. So now what
将信息m异或填充函数P（N,I）
we're gonna do is we're gonna XOR the
message m with some padding function
而N的值是我们派生的，这个填充函数
applied to this value N that we just
derived, at the index I. And this padding
运行非常快。我们完全可以忽略它的运行时间
function is extremely fast. We can pretty
much ignore it in the running time. The
接下来我们就要用密钥K2来加密
next thing we do is we're gonna encrypt
using the key k2. And then we're going
用相同的填充函数P（N,I）再做一次异或
to XOR again, using the same pad. So
we're going to XOR again using the pad
结果就能得到密文，我们统称为C
of N applied to I. And the result is going
to be the cipher text, which we'll denote
而函数P是一个非常简单的函数
by C. Okay, so again as I said, the
function P is some very, very simple
仅仅是在有限域上的一些乘法运算
function. It's just some multiplication in
a finite field which I'm not going to
由于非常非常快，所以由分组密码E的运行决定运行时间
explain here. Very, very fast so the
running time is dominated by the running
这就是XTS，这个结构的好处是
time of the block cipher E and that's it. That's
XTS. And the nice thing about this construction
如果我们想要加密n+1个分组，就需要计算N的值
is now if we wanted to encrypt n plus one
blocks, all we do is we compute the value
对于指数1,2,3,4，我们需要对每一个分组估计PRP E的值
N once. And then for the indices one, two,
three, four basically we just need to
我们需要用变形T1,T2,T3,T4来加密n个分组
evaluate the PRP E once per block. So we
would need to encrypt n blocks using the
我们需要评估n+1个分组密码E
tweaks T,1, T,2, T,3, T,4 and so on. We
would just need n plus one evaluations of
它比小结构还要快两倍
the block cipher E. So it's twice
as fast as the trivial construction.
所以我希望你能认真看XTS结构一分钟
So I want you to stare for just a minute
at this XTS construction. So my question
然后解决一个问题，是不是在使用变形前真有必要对它进行加密？
to you is, is it really necessary to
encrypt the tweak before using it?
下面是一个安全的可调PRP结构
That is, that is the following construction
a secure tweakable PRP. So you can see
在这个结构中可以看到，变形是用于填充函数的输入中的异或过程
in this construction, this tweak is used
directly as input to the padding function
那么如果我们这么做了，这个可调PRP还安全吗？
for the XOR and my question to you is
if we did that, would that be a
给你一点小提示，这是密钥
secure tweakable PRP? And let me
remind you again that, this is the key,
这是变形和数据
this is the tweak and this is the data.
我希望每个人都能得到准确的答案
I hope everybody said that this is the correct answer.
根本上，如果我们将P（t,1）作为数据，我们将其异或上相应的变形
Basically, if we set the data to
be P(t, 1), then when we XOR it with the
就是我们从这里得到的P（t,1），结果为0
corresponding tweak, which is also P(t,1)
we're gonna get here, zero. And so
那么需要加密的就是0，无论这里出来的是什么
what's gonna get encrypted is actually
zero, so whatever that comes out to be.
这里得到的值为C0.那么实际上输出的就是C0异或P（t,1）
Let's say that some value, C0. And
then the actual output is just gonna be C0
现在对P（t,2）重复上述步骤，将得到C0异或P（t,2）
XOR P(t,1). Now when we do the same
thing with P(t, 2), we're gonna get c0
然后将这两者异或，即得到P(t, 1) XOR P(t, 2)
XOR P(t, 2). And when we XOR these two
things together, we just get P(t, 1) XOR P(t, 2).
实际上这意味着攻击者可以直接通过变形和数据查询挑战者
So the fact that this is true means
that an attacker can simply query the
之后就是计算两个响应异或的值
challenger at this tweak and this data,
this tweak and that data. And then just
并将其与合适的填充函数异或值进行比较
compute the XOR of the two responses, and
compare to the XOR of the appropriate
如果相等，我们就与伪随机函数进行交互
padding values. And if the equality holds,
we're interacting with a pseudorandom
否则我们就使其与一个真随机函数交互
function; otherwise we're interacting with
a, with a truly random function. So this
这就允许攻击者利用优势击溃这种结构
would allow the attacker to defeat this
construction with advantage one. So just
总结出XTS适用于磁盘加密
to summarize the way XTS is used for disk
encryption. What we do is we look at
而我们将区数T拆成16字节的分组
sector number T, and we break it into
blocks, sixteen byte blocks. And then
将分组1用变形T1进行加密，变形T2加密分组2
block number one gets encrypted with a
tweak, T1. Block number two gets encrypted
按照这个过程加密下去，每一分组就得到独立的PRP
with a tweak, T2, and so on and so forth.
And so every block gets its own PRP. And
整个区通过PRP集进行加密
the whole sector, as a result, is
encrypted, using, you know, a collection
存在一个PRP水平，但这并不是指一个区水平PRP
of PRPs. Now you notice, this is a block
level PRP. It's not a sector level PRP.
并不是每一个区都通过独立的PRP进行加密
So, in fact, it's not true that each
sector gets encrypted with its own PRP.
而是每一个分组都通过自己独立的PRP进行加密
It's just each block gets encrypted with
its own PRP. The distinction between a
区和分组不同点在于，有些是人为的，XTS模式实际上
sector and a block is some, somewhat
artificial, and this XTS mode actually
提供给你分组的16字节级别上的确定性CPA加密
provides you know, deterministic CPA
encryption at the block level, at the
这是一个目标，这个模式实际上在磁盘加密产品中非常受欢迎
16-byte level. That's the goal. And this
mode actually is fairly popular in disk
我只写几个例子来帮助了解XTS
encryption products. I just wrote a couple
of examples here that actually support
你应该知道磁盘加密常在实践中完成
XTS. So I wanted you to know that this is
in fact how disk encryption is commonly
总结一下，可调加密是一种有用的概念
done in practice. So, to summarize,
tweakable encryption is a useful concept
当你需要许多从单个密钥派生出的独立PRP的时候可用
to know when you need many independent
PRPs all derived from a single key. One
有一点很重要需要记住的是，微结构不是最有效的
important thing to remember is, in fact,
the trivial construction is not the most
由许多类似XTS的结构会更有效率
efficient. There are constructions like
XTS are actually more efficient, where you
你可以批量加密再利用，从一个变形得到许多不同变形加密
can kind of reuse encryptions from one
tweak to get many encryptions for many
这就是使用它们更好的方式
different tweaks. And so those are the
better ways to use them. Both the trivial
微结构和XTS结构都被称作狭窄分组结构
construction and the XTS construction are
what are called narrow block constructions.
即他们提供一个可调分组加密给16字节的分组
Namely they provide a tweakable block
ciphers for a sixteen byte block. But as we
我们看到在最后一段的EME结构中
said, we looked the, at the EME
construction in the last segment, which
为更大的分组提供了一个PRP，事实上EME是一个可调模式操作
provided a PRP for larger, much larger
blocks and in fact EME is a tweakable
如果你需要为更大的分组取得PRP或者是可调PRP，你只需要使用EME
mode of operation. So, if you need PRPs for larger
blocks or tweakable PRPs for larger
但是你应注意，在EME中，你得在每一个输入分组中运用两次分组加密
blocks then you would just use EME. But you
notice there, in EME, you had to apply the
所以它得到结果的速度会比XTS慢一倍
block cipher twice per input block, and
as a result it's twice as slow as
所以它并不是那么常用。这就是有关可调加密的内容
XTS, and is not very often used. So that's
what I wanted to say about tweakable
在下一节中我们会说到保留格式加密
encryption. And in the next segment we'll
talk about format preserving encryption.